Roy Justus Papers
Roy Justus Papers
1931-1983
Justus, 1901-1983
34.5 linear ft.
American editorial cartoonist. Collection contains original editorial cartoons, scrapbooks of editorial cartoons, memorabilia and awards
149093
Biographical History
Roy Braxton Justus (1901-1983) was an award-winning American editorial cartoonist.
Born in Avon, South Dakota in 1901, Justus had his first exhibition while still in high school, a selection of cartoons about World War I displayed in the local drugstore. He attended Morningside College in Sioux City, Iowa and went to work as a cartoonist for the Sioux City Tribune where he stayed for 17 years with brief stints in Washington D.C. and in New York with the Associated Press. In 1944, after three years with the Sioux City Journal, Justus became the editorial cartoonist for the Minneapolis Star. His editorial cartoons were also syndicated to newspapers around the United States through the Register and Tribune Syndicate.
Justus served as vice president and president of the newly formed American Association of Editorial Cartoonists (AAEC). He was also a member of the National Cartoonists Society, the National Press Club and the Minneapolis Press Club. His work was recognized by several organizations. Justus received the 1965 Sigma Delta Chi Award, several Freedom Foundation awards, the National Headliner’s Club Award and the Christopher Award. Morningside College presented him with an honorary doctorate of letters in 1965.
Justus retired from his duties at the Minneapolis Star in 1975 and died on May 19, 1983.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Roy Justus Papers represent three decades of Justus' career as an editorial cartoonist. In addition to providing a window into Justus' artistic and journalistic career, the collection also documents, in correspondence and photographs, Justus' relationship with president Lyndon Johnson.
Artwork (1938-1975) is subdivided into works by Justus and works by Others. The majority are original editorial cartoons by Justus for the Minneapolis Star Tribune. There is one box of Justus' work for the Sioux City Journal. Most pieces of artwork have dates written or stamped on the back; the years 1942-1946 have been arranged alphabetically by caption, as they are undated. Sioux City Journal artwork is undated but from approximately 1941-1943. Justus usually worked in ink and crayon on illustration board, using thin lines with an image size of 9” x 10 ½”. Captions are written in pencil or ink. Interleaves are original, as received from the donor.
Also in this series are individual cartoons by other artists inscribed to Justus.
Correspondence (1931-1983) contains incoming correspondence and selected replies from Justus. Topics include requests for permissions and other business matters, and responses from readers who frequently included clippings of his editorial cartoons with their specific complaints. There are scattered insulting drawings referring to him as the "king of hate." One frequent correspondent is Willie Day Taylor, President Lyndon Johnson’s assistant, asking for original cartoons for LBJ’s personal collection. There are also letters from Hubert Humphrey and Richard Nixon, IBM, the Encyclopedia Britannica, cartoonists Rollin Kirby and Jay “Ding” Darling. A number of letters are from Syracuse University Library staff about the donation of the collection, and there is one letter about Justus’ death, addressed to his wife.
Memorabilia (1944-1975) consists of awards, photographs and printed material. Included here are awards in various forms (e.g. medals) from the Freedom Foundation, Sigma Chi Delta and the National Headliners Club, and associated printed material related to recognitions. Also in this series are 51 scrapbooks (1941-1969) containing daily clippings of Justus' editorial cartoons. There is also one scrapbook of other material.
Of particular interest are the photographs, including pictures of Justus at the Johnson presidential library, Justus with Richard Nixon and Hubert Humphrey circa 1959, AAEC events, cartoonists at the Cape Kennedy Missile Test Annex and portraits of Justus. There are also two candid color snapshots showing Lyndon Johnson behind the wheel of a convertible, with Justus and others in the car including Albany Times Union cartoonist Hy Rosen. The photos from June 1971 were taken at Johnson’s Texas ranch. Almost all the photographs are black and white 8x10s.
Printed material (1921-1975) contains primarily clippings about Justus and his work, and mailings from the AAEC. Included is a review of a Herblock book written by Justus and editorials from newspapers that directly reference Justus, such as published letters to the editor about Justus' work.
The small Miscellaneous series contains indexes, exhibition miscellany, and notes.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons from the years 1942-1946 have been arranged alphabetically, as they are undated. Cartoons from the years 1947-1975 are in chronological order. Correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by sender. Files of reader responses are in chronological order.
Related Material
has more than 150 collections of cartoonists' papers. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
The following published items have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging:
"The University of Miami's Lowe Art Museum presents the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists in exhibit," call number: NC1427 .C67 1968
"The Great Challenge," as seen by international cartoonists from more than 20 countries, call number: NC1355 .I5 1958
"American editorial cartoons," a catalogue of an exhibition held at American Embassy, London, May 11- 22, 1970, and organized by the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists, call number: NC1427 .L65 1970
"Drawn and Quartered: the world of the British Newspaper cartoon," catalogue of an exhibit at the National Portrait Gallery in London, 13 May to 31 July 1970, call number: NC1477 .L65 1970
Subject and Genre Headings
Justus, 1901-1983.; Sioux City journal (Sioux City, Iowa: 1887); Minneapolis star and tribune.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Minneapolis Star and Tribune Co., 1965-1977 and Mrs. Roy Justus, 1988.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - By Justus
    - 1942-1944, from Sioux City Journal; 53 items (Oversize 2)
      America's highest honor
      Among the casualties
      Beginning to see the light, Tojo?
      "Bonanza"
      Bringing them back alive!
      Chief of the gremlins
      Dancing master
      The "dietitian"
      The dog and his reflection
      The "dove"
      Engineering problem
      Fiddling
      The fightin' kid
      "Gid-dap!"
      The greased pig
      Hiding behind her skirts
      Hirohito's zoo
      How deep is our well?
      How's fishing, Adolf?
      Joe's new blend
      Leap year
      Looks like the only recourse
      May be a vacation would do 'em both some good
      Mountain climbing has its hazards!
      News item: "American and British forces meet"
      No sale
      "Now, ain't that too bad!"
      Now is the time to redouble our efforts!
      On the home front
      The outcast
      Pianissimo
      Pistol packin' mama
      Refreshing his memory
      The rude awakening
      Sailor, beware
      Satan reproving sin
      Self-styled military strategist
      Shades of St. Patrick
      Shake hands with the devil
      Sixty-four dollar question
      State's responsibility
      Taking the bull by the horns
      That "sleeping-sickness" bug is here again
      Two sphinxes are twice as silent as one!
      Uncle's little helpers
      U. S. Navy
      Victory gardening
      "Vot do you mean - second front?"
      The "war don't mean nothing to me!
      What are you going to do about it?
      Whole hog
      Wrong number
      Yes - let us be thankful!
    - Before 1946, 77 items (Oversize 2)
      Anxious moment
      At home
      Atom by the tail
      At the Vitale
      Back to the sewers
      Banking the fire with coal
      Black market
      Busy hen with one chick
      Chivalry in a war-torn world
      Discharged production chief
      Disturbing influence
      Double shot
      The dunce
      Easter bonnet
      Essence of simplicity
      Europe
      Fine reception committee
      Five years in a barroom
      Fishing for the one that got away
      Fishing isn't very exciting this season
      Fortissimo!
      Guide that failed
      Handyman
      Here, you take over
      His last laugh
      Hitchhiker
      Hope springs eternal
      "I think I see someone coming!"
      In desperation
      "in giving freedom to the slave we assure freedom to the free"
      In the same boat
      It's going to take a lot of delousing!
      Let's practice non-fraternization here
      Little Miss Muffett
      Lost week-end
      Man on horseback
      Man with the hoe
      More mouths than worms
      The morning after
      "My valentine!"
      Neat trick, but - gosh!
      Not the least of the victims
      Now, more than ever
      "Oh, the farmer in the dell!"
      Old hat for mademoiselle
      Open season
      Open season again
      The outcasts
      Poor teacher
      Saving face
      "See - it really won't be so bad!"
      So it may be ours to use
      State of the union
      Still in the hands of the architect
      Still on that detour
      Stout heart
      The tail does wag the dog
      Taps for corporal Hitler
      "Thanks!"
      Thriving on starvation
      Time again for heroism
      Time off to observe St. Patrick's day
      Tugging at his own bootstraps
      Unbalanced diet
      Under the guns
      Valuable salvage
      Vaporizing effect of the atomic bomb
      Victory march
      Victory and peace
      Wanted: good man to fill important position
      We can stand a change of expressions!
      "What a wonderful bird is the pelican"
      What the well-dressed man will wear
      Why the priority?
      With but a single thought
      World politics
      "Your fleet guarantees freedom"
    - 1946, 37 items (Oversize 3)
      Jan 1: Happy new era!
      Jan 12: Finest pullin' team in the world
      Jan 17: We've got the know-how!
      Jan 30: How to let go and when?
      Mar 18: Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde
      Apr 4: Tidal waves
      May 2: Ruining a perfectly delightful picnic
      May 4: National headache
      May 17: Pussy's only choice
      May 21: Exploding the ostrich myth
      May 25: Peace hath her victories
      May 31: Another shift
      Jun 1: Home to roost
      Jul 18: Babe in the woods
      Jul 24: The call of the wind
      Jul 27: La-de-e-e-ez- an' gen-tle-mun-n-n
      Aug 9: Weaning must come sometime
      Aug 21: A tree grows in Minneapolis
      Aug 23: The trials of nurse-maiding
      Aug 24: A tough one for David
      Aug 27: Bodyguard for his adolescence
      Aug 28: Sleepless nights
      Sep 24: Meet my buddy
      Oct 2: Tethered
      Oct 9: New neighborhood market
      Nov 11: Insecure refuge
      Nov 14: Keep the lid on
      Nov 16: The new pianist
      Nov 23: Let him fly
      Nov 26: One brownout the nation could endure
      Nov 29: The hare and the tortoise and john l.
      Dec 3: Smilin' through
      Dec 4: Still plenty of heat
      Dec 5: The under miner
      Dec 6: One man's poison may be another man's meat
      Dec 11: World's champion flagpole sitter
      Dec 30: Satellite
    - 1947, 66 items (Oversize 3)
      Jan 8: And no place to throw it
      Jan 23: Stupendous and colossal
      Jan 30: Atom arms race
      Feb 6: Expensive fiddler
      Feb 12: I tell ya - that fella didn't know his own strength
      Feb 13: Erosion cuts deeply
      Feb 14: Great day for Dan Cupid
      Feb 21: What about the other fifty-one weeks
      Mar 1: Problem: how to restore his health - but not his strength?
      Mar 2: The hard fact
      Mar 5: Joshua commands the sun to stand still
      Mar 11: Good-bye!
      Mar 12: Headless horseman
      Mar 16: Pied piper
      Mar 26: Watch your aim, uncle!
      Mar 27: Not this!
      Mar 29: Still feeling his oats
      Apr 2: A bicycle built for two
      Apr 12: Somebody's going to get hurt
      Apr 20: Restless nesting place
      Apr 23: Striking while the iron is hot
      Apr 28: The little four
      May 2: Dangerous alarm clock
      May 4: Scarecrow
      May 9: Bossism is bossism whatever the label
      May 10: Temptation, the test of character
      May 13: Heavy, heavy
      May 25: Springtime
      May 27: Easy come, easy go!
      Jun 1: Liberty bell
      Jun 11: About every four years
      Jun 13: Who, me?
      Jun 14: The laboratory's by-product
      Jun 15: Operation free world
      Jun 19: Till death do us part
      Jun 29: Here's a brush for you, tom, tom sawyer
      Jun 30: The race
      Jul 4: Where liberty is not taken lightly
      Jul 7: The cynic
      Jul 13: Maiden in distress
      Jul 14: Humpty dumpty
      Jul 15: Concentration
      Jul 25: International book-of-the-year
      Jul 27: Must world unity wait for this
      Aug 3: First the one and then the other
      Aug 8: The 64 trillion dollar question
      Aug 10: The crucial point of evolution
      Aug 14: Uncle won it two years ago
      Aug 16: The more abundant life
      Aug 30: Is this your hired man?
      Sep 1: A study in posture
      Sep 3: Big stick - and a secret. Too!
      Oct 3: Mr. Big
      Oct 4: He carries two bags
      Oct 5: End of the trail
      Oct 9: Hasn't even sobered up from the last bust
      Oct 16: Events that could make big news
      Oct 26: The man who came to dinner
      Oct 29: That immutable law at work
      Nov 15: Who done it?
      Nov 17: Vanguard
      Nov 18: Yes, spinach
      Nov 30: Uncle Joe's oyster stew
      Dec 16: See, we've got our economy under control!
      Dec 25: Indomitable spirit
      Dec 29: Is this all we can do about it?
    - 1948, 113 items (Oversize 4)
      Jan 2: Looks like an early spring!
      Jan 6: Where did you get the umbrella?
      Jan 15: Not his language
      Jan 17: The goose: I thought this was a refuge!
      Jan 21: Still a game of chance
      Jan 21: The open door
      Jan 27: Is this not a dainty dish?
      Feb 8: Butter or guns
      Feb 25: Problem child
      Mar 14: Cannon to right of him, cannon to left of him.
      Mar 16: Isn't the skating season about over?
      Mar 23: March winds
      Mar 24: Bravo!
      Mar 30: Requires a strong perch
      Apr 1: The hitch-hiker
      Apr 6: Tributes to the general
      Apr 8: Presidential primaries
      Apr 9: Still champion weight lifter
      Apr 11: The issue
      Apr 17: Posting a bill on the iron curtain
      Apr 19: John, there's somebody snooping!
      Apr 20: Immovable object and irresistible force?
      Apr 21: A free-booter gets the boot
      Apr 22: A little tough on the challenger
      Apr 23: You can hardly tell it from vodka!
      Apr 24: Witch's brew
      Apr 25: Hope springs eternal
      Apr 26: Delivering the goods
      Apr 28: Plenty of fielding
      Apr 30: Suspended animation
      May 2: Whistling past the graveyard
      May 4: Picture of a gentleman unscrambling an omelet
      May 5: Hey, you hounds - I want a shot at that rabbit
      May 9: Joe doesn't know Uncle Sam
      May 11: The race
      May 12: Oasis or another mirage?
      May 13: Trying to hitch his wagon to some stars
      May 14: In the merry month of may
      May 16: Joe doesn't understand our boxing matches
      May 17: If only he'd go fishing!
      May 18: Which is it going to be
      May 19: Skeptical but hopeful
      May 20: Here we go again!
      May 21: While we're on the subject of rubbish
      May 23: This race is to the swift
      May 25: The guiding hand
      May 26: Ever-blooming
      May 28: The seat they are fighting over
      May 29: Ordnance expert
      Jun 1: Ever expanding horizons
      Jun 6: And a side show, too!
      Jun 7: Not his master's!
      Jun 8: Still chasing his tail
      Jun 12: June
      Jun 13: The vice
      Jun 17: Your campaign button is showing, mister!
      Jun 19: All roads
      Jun 24: Ladies and gentlemen
      Jun 25: Twice did he accept the crown
      Jun 28: The democrats inherit a haunted house
      Jul 6: Forecast: continued hot
      Jul 10: Why don't you take a vacation?
      Jul 11: Perish the thought
      Jul 12: Not a very auspicious beginning!
      Jul 14: No caption
      Jul 16: The donkey is on the offensive
      Jul 17: The opening gun
      Jul 18: Harry's babysitter
      Jul 21: The bait
      Jul 24: In convention assembled
      Jul 25: National goldfish bowl
      Jul 27: Charlie McWallace
      Aug 1: May be it is just convalescent cussedness!
      Aug 11: Versatile Volga boatman
      Aug 13: Not on his beat?
      Aug 16: Why should I arouse suspicion?
      Sep 14: Test of nerve
      Sep 15: Playing favorites
      Sep 16: Turned to quicksand
      Sep 20: Harry's furrow
      Sep 29: Voice of experience
      Oct 5: Time is of the essence
      Oct 8: Prize melon
      Oct 11: The wayward bus
      Oct 14: Always something to take the joy out of life
      Oct 18: Beginning of understanding?
      Oct 22: Home to roost
      Oct 23: Always that intruder
      Oct 26: What the well dressed man should wear?
      Oct 27: Balance for Marianne
      Oct 28: Harry's Halloween prank
      Oct 29: The accuser
      Nov 2: Two kinds of curtains
      Nov 3: This is my strength, Joe!
      Nov 11: Still looking for the dove
      Nov 12: Doc Stalin, nerve specialist
      Nov 13: Make way for the lady
      Nov 15: The firebug and the fireman
      Nov 18: Thanksgiving is just around the corner
      Nov 19: Man with a hoe
      Nov 20: Busy bee keeper
      Nov 22: Still unscrambling the omelet
      Nov 30: How times have changed
      Dec 7: Tin-canned again!
      Dec 8: Round four coming up!
      Dec 9: Maybe it's only a nightmare
      Dec 13: Page from the Bierstadt committee report
      Dec 15: The good earth
      Dec 17: A meeting we'd like to see
      Dec 25: How strong the manacle?
      Dec 29: Lullaby
      May 1: Do your Christmas mailing early (listed in inventory; not found in box)
      May 1: Speaking of coat tails
    - 1949, 104 items (Oversize 5)
      Jan 1: What a grumpy old fellow!
      Jan 5: State of the union
      Jan 14: Any volunteers for this ice-cap rescue?
      Jan 24: Sword of Damocles
      Jan 31: The thinker
      Feb 1: Ever hear the story about the talking bear?
      Feb 9: When the doctors disagree
      Feb 11: Everybody to the rescue!
      Feb 12: A thought for the day
      Feb 17: Remember the constitution
      Feb 21: Befuddled blacksmith
      Feb 24: Harry: you're the worst donkey in history!
      Mar 4: Forced feeding
      Mar 5: His master's voice
      Mar 8: Let's agree to clip our wings!
      Mar 9: One expert seems to be as good as another
      Mar 11: Boarding house reach
      Mar 17: Flowers that bloom in the spring, tra-la
      Mar 19: His beat
      Mar 21: And that means you!
      Mar 22: Hope springs eternal
      Mar 24: First and second fiddlers
      Mar 25: The Ned Bold look
      Apr 4: Going to take some persuasion
      Apr 5: Seven league boots
      Apr 7: The big difference
      Apr 12: Memo
      Apr 16: Easter bonnet
      Apr 20: Here comes another spitball
      Apr 22: That stuff is intoxicating, too!
      Apr 23: The dawn comes up like thunder
      Apr 27: His one last hope
      May 3: May flowers
      May 4: Remarkable recuperative flowers
      May 6: Not too warm a handshake
      May 10: The gambler
      May 12: Somebody needs a public relations expert
      May 16: For a short time, anyway
      May 26: Vodka to warm his spirits
      May 27: Stronger than any curtain
      May 28: The east and the west are still meeting
      Jun 4: Well, it's about time
      Jun 6: How to divide the worm
      Jun 9: Can it happen here
      Jun 16: Cradle of civilization
      Jul 5: Fiddling
      Jul 16: Confused traveler
      Jul 18: Where do you think you are going?
      Jul 23: Lest we forget
      Jul 25: Is the tail wagging the dog?
      Jul 27: Be careful, boys - it's loaded
      Aug 1: Music hath charms
      Aug 4: Bigger and bolder
      Aug 5: Hot and humid
      Aug 8: Making hay
      Aug 11: Here comes another landslide
      Aug 16: His greatest enemy
      Aug 20: More good neighbor policy in the east
      Sep 6: You can't fight ideas with a club
      Sep 9: Problems within problems
      Sep 12: From one good neighbor to another
      Sep 13: Out, damned spot! Out, I say!
      Sep 16: Green pastures
      Sep 17: Helping him to help himself
      Sep 18: Beast of burden
      Sep 21: Lead off man
      Sep 23: Is there a psychiatrist in the house
      Sep 24: No place to hide
      Sep 27: The bear came over the mountain
      Sep 30: Christopher Columbus was a piker
      Oct 1: Transformation of an inferiority complex?
      Oct 25: The iceman cometh and cometh
      Oct 26: Good nesting place
      Oct 27: Yo-yo
      Oct 29: Team! Team! Team!
      Nov 1: Isn't a woman's work ever done?
      Nov 2: Louder!
      Nov 4: East indies windfall
      Nov 5: Mr. Truman's non-political twin cities speech
      Nov 14: But where will Uncle Sam get his security
      Nov 15: Statue of slavery
      Nov 17: Interplanetary relations might bring startling results
      Nov 18: Time and tide-and science
      Nov 23: Heads I win, tails you lose
      Nov 24: So that others may have a thanksgiving, too
      Nov 25: The shield
      Nov 26: And now that refreshing old act
      Nov 29: Slightly ruffled dignity
      Dec 1: The second phase
      Dec 2: Merry Christmas
      Dec 3: That's bad advice, john!
      Dec 5: Bird in a gilded cage
      Dec 6: Hard to swat a bee with a club
      Dec 7: Open house for our foreign friends
      Dec 8: Well, why not?
      Dec 10: Will it come to this?
      Dec 11: Hearin' things!
      Dec 12: A big ear to the ground
      Dec 16: Fancy meeting you here!
      Dec 21: Competition
      Dec 23: Snowbound
      Dec 24: Twas the night before...
      Dec 26: Who left the backdoor open?
      Dec 30: New year's resolution
    - 1950 Jan-Jun, 108 items (Oversize 6)
      Jan 2: Mercy - another one!
      Jan 3: Bag and baggage
      Jan 4: Oriental King Canute
      Jan 7: No caption
      Jan 9: The lady and the dragon
      Jan 13: The embrace of death
      Jan 18: The rigors of the ice fishing
      Jan 25: The rescue
      Jan 28: Moving right in!
      Jan 31: No sign of budging
      Feb 2: Most any time now
      Feb 4: Naturally, there are strings attached
      Feb 6: Co-authoring the tax bill
      Feb 7: The finish line
      Feb 10: Little Jack Horner is going to get sick
      Feb 13: Joe's awfully busy right now
      Feb 15: The assault
      Feb 16: Snow from two points of view
      Feb 17: Mutual assistance pack
      Feb 18: How times have changed
      Feb 23: Curbstone repartee
      Feb 25: Hope springs eternal
      Feb 27: It's a cruel world
      Feb 28: How will you have your potatoes?
      Mar 4: There he goes again
      Mar 6: In this fickle month of march
      Mar 11: What do you have in mind, john?